Guide to the Emma Toedteberg bookplate collection, 1701-1982 2012.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Emma Toedteberg bookplate collection
Bulk, 1870-1936
1701-1982
2012.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
23.5 Linear feet in 48 manuscript boxes.
The Emma Toedteberg Bookplate collection, spanning from 1701 to 1982, was the bookplate collection of long-time Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) librarian Emma Toedteberg (1856-1936). The collection was originally created by Miss Toedteberg's father, Augustus Toedteberg (1824-1909), and later expanded by BHS librarians. The present collection numbers over 7,000 bookplates ranging from the eighteenth to the twentieth century, including armorial, heraldic and presentation bookplates of individuals and institutions. Works of numerous engravers are represented such as Edwin Davis French, Charles W. Sherborn and John W. Evans.
Huntington, Edna, 1895-1965
Stryker-Rodda, Harriet
Toedteberg, Augustus, 1823 or 4-1909
Toedteberg, Emma
Biographical/Historical note
Emma Toedteberg (1857-1936) joined the staff of the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) at the age of 13. Following the tenure of George Hannah, she served as the Society's third librarian from 1889 until her death. Toedteberg was an avid proponent of animal rights and a member of the Protestant Episcopal Church of the Nativity in Brooklyn. She also inherited from her father a passion for collecting bookplates.
Augustus Toedteberg (1824-1909), her father, emigrated from Germany in 1844 and worked as an inlay illustrator in New York City. He married fellow German immigrant Catherine Lager (d. 1905) in New York City in 1849. In addition to Emma, the couple had another daughter, Louise Toedteberg (1853-1938). The family resided at 274 Vanderbilt Avenue in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, and later at 628 East Delmere Place (now known as East 23rd Street) in Flatbush. Harriet Stryker-Rodda was the Long Island Historical Society librarian in the 1960s, and published books on genealogy research, Brooklyn church records and a guide to colonial handwriting.
Harriet Styker-Rodda was the Long Island Historical Society librarian in the 1960s, and published books on genealogical research, Brooklyn church records and guides to colonial handwritting.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into six series, and maintains a previous arrangement of the materials into boxes, folders and archival sleeves and envelopes. The plates are loosely alphabetized in each box, and are mounted on paper unless otherwise indicated.
Series 1: Engravers of Bookplates
Series 2: Non-illustrated Bookplates
Series 3: Illustrated Bookplates
Series 4: Ladies' Bookplates
Series 5: Institutional Bookplates
Series 6: Indexes and Papers
Scope and Contents
The Emma Toedteberg bookplate collection is comprised of an estimated 7,000 bookplates dating back to the early 18th century. Originally created by Miss Toedteberg's father, Augustus Toedteberg, the collection was expanded in the 1960s by librarian Harriet Stryker-Rodda, wife of the Society's then vice president Kenn Stryker-Rodda. Loosely alphabetized and organized by subject, the collection includes armorial, heraldic and presentation bookplates of individuals and institutions, and the works of numerous engravers such as Edwin Davis French, Charles W. Sherborn and John W. Evans. Arranged with the bookplates is a series of previously compiled indexes, which provide a comprehensive point of entry into researching the collection, along with related papers and correspondence.
The collection represents the culture of American and British book collecting for both personal and institutional libraries, from the colonial era through World War I. The abundant patterns of artistic styles, bookplate types and printing techniques reflect a unique modern history of the graphic arts. As many of the bookplate owners are persons of artistic, financial and political consequence, the collection offers a distinct perspective on social and class history.
Included are the bookplates of prominent Brooklyn figures such as Bishop Cadman and Henry Ward Beecher; early New York figures colonial like Governor Cadwallader Colden, Mayor James Duane, and John Pintard, a founder of the New York Historical Society; and artistic personalities such as magician Harry Houdini, Hollywood performers Douglas Fairbanks and Mary Pickford, and Broadway impresario David Belasco. Included are the bookplates of United States Presidents John Quincy Adams, Martin Van Buren and Theodore Roosevelt; Adam Smith, author of The Wealth of Nations; Captain James Cook, the eighteenth-century explorer, and Marie Antoinette. Also featured are the institutional bookplates of the Brooklyn Historical Society; The New York Society Library, the oldest private library in New York City; The American Museum of Natural History; and the Brooklyn Club.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Louise Toedteberg, 1936.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Archival Materials note
The following volumes provide a rich source of background material on bookplates and the culture of book-collecting, and can be found in the library collection of the Brooklyn Historical Society:
Bowdoin, W.G. (April, 1940) "Emma Toedteberg and her Bookplates," The Long Island Historical Society Quarterly, April, 1940, no. 2. (Brooklyn Historical Society Main Collection, F116 .L875 Non-circulating)
Fincham, H.W. (1897) The Artists and Engravers of British and American Book Plates. Private printing. (Uncatalogued)
Rawls, Walton H. (1964) The Century Book. The Long Island Historical Society. See chapter 4, "The Society's Bookplates," by North, Edgerton G. (Brooklyn Historical Society Reference - Desk, F116.L66 C46 1964 c.2 Non-circulating)
Scott, Temple (1902) "The Artistic Book-Plate," in Bookplates of Today, Stone, W.M. (ed.) NY: Tonnelle & Co. (Uncatalogued)
Stone, Wilbur Macey (1902) Women Designers of Book-Plates. NY: The Triptych. (Brooklyn Historical Society Main Collection, Z993 .S89 1902 Non-circulating)
Teall, Gardner (1921) Bookplates by Sidney L. Smith. Kansas City: Alfred Fowler. (Uncatalogued)
Ward, Harry Parker (1915) Some American College Bookplates. Columbus, OH: The Champlin Press. (Uncatalogued)
Also useful is the library's collection of journals and periodicals devoted to bookplates, which includes The Bookplate Chronicle (1922-1925), and Ex Libris (circa 1890s). (Uncatalogued)
In addition, numerous resources can be found online. The following sites were last accessed Aug. 30, 2011:
http://bookplatejunkie.blogspot.com/
http://www.bookplate.org/
http://uvamagazine.org/only_online/article/ex_libris/
http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/bsuva/related.html
http://www.sharpweb.org/en/resources/series-journals.html
http://www.bibsocamer.org/BibSite/bibsite.htm
http://www.thebookcollector.co.uk/index.html
http://www.bibsocamer.org/BibSite/Pearson/Pearson.pdf
http://www.bookplatesociety.org/resources.htm
http://www.bookplatesociety.org/styles.html
http://www.pietafineart.com/sherborn.htm
http://www.americanantiquarian.org/Findingaids/sidney_lawton_smith.pdf
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Long Island Historical Society.; Art |z Collectors and collecting |z United States; Art, American; Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bookplates; Engravings; Graphic artists |z New York (State) |z New York; Heraldry; Photographs; Portraits
- Series 1: Engravers of Bookplates, 1831-1943; 4.5 Linear feet in 9 manuscript boxes
  Arrangement note
  Organized into seven sub-series, these bookplates are arranged by the individual engraver: Edwin Davis French, Charles W. Sherborn, Walter M. Aikman, George W. Eve, John W. Evans, Sidney Lawton Smith, Joseph Winfred Spenceley.
  Scope and Contents
  The engravers are American and English. Walter Aikman and John Evans lived in Brooklyn, and Edwin D. French designed the bookplate of Emma Toedteberg.
  - Subseries 1: Edwin Davis French, circa 1870s-1906; 2.0 Linear feet in 4 manuscript boxes. (Box 1 - 4)
    Loosely alphabetized by bookplate owner.
    The illustrated bookplate of Emma Toedteberg is featured in the French collection. Also, in Box 2, in the folder for the bookplate of Harvey Cushing, there is a presentation bookplate inscribed in pencil "with compliments of E.D. French to Miss Emma Toedteberg." Includes illustrated bookplates. A sample of French plates in the collection: American Institute of Electrical Engineers, Long Island Historical Society, Storrs fund, Club of Odd Volumes, Helen Elvira Brainerd.
    Biographical/Historical note
    Bookplates designed and engraved by Edwin Davis French (1851-1906), who engraved the personal bookplate of Emma Toedteberg. Born in New England, French attended Brown University for one year before finding work as an engraver of silverware for the Whiting Company in Massachussetts. In 1876, French relocated to New York City and studied at the Art Students' League, where he later served as President. He was introduced to the art of bookplates by his sister-in-law, Helen Elvira Brainerd, who organized a collection of American and European ex-libris for the library of Columbia University. In addition to the over 200 bookplates French engraved and designed for collectors and institutions, French designed plates for his personal collection of international language books, with an emphasis on Volapuk, a constructed language devised in 1879 by a German priest. Among French’s work are bookplates for St. Paul's Chapel, on Lower Broadway in Manhattan; Fraunces’ Tavern, a Revolutionary War eatery and museum; and the New York Police Department’s Central Booking, known as ‘The Tombs.”
    Sources:
    The Autobiography of Edwin Davis French (1901)
    Edwin Davis French, A Memorial (1906) by Mary Brainerd French
  - Subseries 2: Charles W. Sherborn, circa 1870s-1912; 0.25 Linear feet in .5 manuscript box. (Box 5)
    Bookplates engraved by Charles Sherborn, including illustrated bookplates.
    Born in London, Charles Sherborn (1831-1912) began work as a goldsmith, chiefly engraving jewelry, but after problems with his business in 1872, Sherborn turned to etching and engraving reproductions of other artist’s works. Sherborn began engraving bookplates late in his career, and between the early 1880’s and 1912 the artist produced over 350 bookplates, the bulk of his work in the armorial style.
    http://www.pietafineart.com/sherborn.htm (last accessed August 30, 2011)
  - Subseries 3: Walter M. Aikman, circa 1870s-1930s; 0.25 Linear feet in .5 manuscript box. (Box 5)
    Bookplates engraved by Walter Aikman, including Aikman's personal bookplate, several illustrated bookplates, as well as correspondence between the engraver and Emma Toedteberg.
    Aikman (1857-1939) lived at 133 Macon Street in Brooklyn, Bedford-Stuyvesant, and studied in Paris. In A Directory of Bookplate Artists, with notes concerning their work (1921), edited and compiled by Alfred Fowler, Aikman provided the following statement: "I engrave bookplates on copper and wood and also etch them. I do not specialize. The cost depends on the time a given design takes to complete. I have been making bookplates for about eight or ten years."
  - Subseries 4: George W. Eve, circa 1870s-1914; 0.25 Linear feet in .5 manuscript box. (Box 5)
    Bookplates engraved by George W. Eve.
    Born in England, G.W. Eve (1855-1914) also published books and pamphlets on the subject of heraldry.
  - Subseries 5: John W. Evans, circa 1870s-1943; 0.25 Linear feet in .5 manuscript box. (Box 5)
    Loosely alphabetized by bookplate owner, and arranged in sleeves marked "Aikman and Eve."
    Bookplates engraved by John W. Evans.
    Evans (1855-1943) was an award-winning artist and wood-cut engraver who lived on St. Marks Avenue in Brooklyn. A distinguished Freemason, Evans provided illustrations for turn of the century weekly magazines, and was noted as the last of a generation of flourishing woodcut artists from the late nineteenth century.
    Source: Scrapbook Collection, Brooklyn Historical Society,
  - Subseries 6: Sidney Lawton Smith, circa 1860s-1920s; 1.0 Linear feet in 2 manuscript boxes. (Box 6 - 7)
    Bookplates engraved and designed by Sidney Lawton Smith, including illustrated plates and plates for the American Antiquarian Society and Boston Public Library.
    One of the most highly-regarded line-engravers of his time, Smith (1845-1929) often designed the bookplates he engraved. Working from Boston, Mass, Smith also designed stained-glass for church buildings, and designed the seal for The Society of Iconophiles, a private New York club of book and print collectors.
  - Subseries 7: Joseph Winfred Spenceley, circa 1880s-1908; 1.0 Linear feet in 2 manuscript boxes. (Box 8 - 9)
    Bookplates designed and engraved by J.W. Spenceley, including handwritten correspondence from Spenceley to Emma in Box 6, with a promotional pamphlet for a coming 1904 private publication on Spenceley. Along with the engraver's own bookplate, a sample of the collection includes the plates of Oliver Wendell Holmes, the Detroit Public Library, the New Theatre in New York City, and the Zeta Psi Club.
    In “A Visit to Mr. Spenceley’s Study,” published in The Book-Plate Booklet (vol 1, no 3, ed. by Sheldon Cheney Nov.1906 - Nov. 1907), the engraver (1865–1908) is profiled:
    "A three-mile ride over the hills from the railroad station brings one to the summer studio of Mr. J. W. Spenceley of Boston, who has etched and engraved many notable book-plates during the last dozen years. The cottage is on a hillside, just above the quiet New Hampshire village of Chocorua…. I found him sitting beneath an apple tree, making studies of a grape vine that climbed over a boulder near by…. We passed through the spacious living-room, where hung water-colors, and prints from the book-plate work of some of the noted engravers, and continuing upstairs, reached the studio…. Mr. Spenceley placed four copper plates before me, each different in design. ‘You see the variety, but each holds my interest. Perhaps I like landscape plates best, and grace and treatment of the sixth-century French designs appeal to me especially. However, to incorporate artistically the ideas of my clientele, I find it better to use various forms of design rather than to hold to any one style’…. It is small wonder one feels the exquisite harmony in his book-plates, for he is one of Nature's most earnest lovers, and only embodies in his work the happiest and most beautiful aspects of life.”
- Series 2: Non-Illustrated Bookplates, 1701-circa 1936; 9.5 Linear feet in 19 manuscript boxes (Box Box 10-24, 44-45)
  Except where noted, these plates are mounted and do not include associated information about the subject. The American bookplates were owned by men who lived primarily during the mid-19th century through the early 1930s, and include bookplates owned by surgeons, professors, bankers and editors. The English owners lived primarily in the 19th century. The unmounted plates include individual men's and institutional plates, and Box 44 and 45 have "unmounted duplicates," which include numerous Emma and Augustus Toedteberg duplicates and presentation plates to the Long Island Historical Society.
  The plates of various states are printed directly to the paper rather than mounted. The "oversize" plates are printed on 8 x 11 cardstock. A "state" refers to the printing process, where an impression is made from the original design to create a print. Different states result from changes to the original design. Copies of many of these plates are boxed elsewhere in the collection. Included are several duplicates of Emma Toedteberg's personal bookplates, as well as the bookplates of ladies and institutions.
  Box 45 includes correspondence between librarian Edna Huntington and the College of Arms in London, dated 1951, regarding Ms. Huntington's research request to identify a coat-of-arms depicted in a particular bookplate. The box also includes a letter to Emma Toedteberg from Northwestern University Library, dated April 24, 1922; and a handwritten note dated January 29, 1925, lacking letterhead.
  Organized according to an original order of American bookplate owners, followed by English owners, unmounted bookplates, and bookplates of various states and sizes. Each box is alphabetized by bookplate owner.
- Series 3: Illustrated Bookplates, 1701-circa 1936; 6.5 Linear feet in 13 manuscript boxes (Box 28 - 40)
  The bulk of the collection consists of bookplates described as "illustrated," which indicates that the bookplate is mounted and accompanied by any one or more of the following materials: a photo or portrait of the bookplate owner or institution, an obituary of biographical note or clipping, a sample signature or autograph. These bookplates include male and female individuals as well as institutions, and are the chief source of plates in the collection owned by notable or historical personalities, such as Lord Byron, J.P. Morgan, H.L. Mencken, and Gouveneur Morris.
- Series 4: Ladies' Bookplates, 1700s-circa 1936; 1.25 Linear feet in 2.5 manuscript boxes (Box 25, 41-42)
  The ladies plates are organized as mounted and unmounted, each box loosely alphabetized according to bookplate owner.
  The non-illustrated bookplates have been previously organized between male and female book-owners. Some of the ladies' mounted plates include a handwriting sample. While the men's bookplates are often of a more stately and familiar design, employing armorial patterns rooted in Western Europe, the ladies' bookplates tend to be of a more expressive and original nature, unconstrained by tradition. Topless sirens call to distant ships on the ladies' bookplates, where the men's show shields, lions' heads and foliage. Also, this collection includes the joint bookplates of married couples, which have been filed according to the wife rather than the husband.
  - Mounted, 1700s-1936; 0.75 Linear feet in 1.5 manuscript boxes. (Box 41-42)
  - Unmounted, 1700s-1936; 0.5 Linear feet in 1 manuscript box (Box 25)
- Series 5: Institutional Bookplates, 1759-1936; 0.75 Linear feet in 1.5 manuscript boxes (Box 42-43)
  These institutions include libraries, societies, colleges & universities, private clubs and museums: the Brooklyn Historical Society (previously known as the Long Island Historical Society); the Bohemian Club, San Francisco, CA; the Newark, NJ Free Public Library; the Salmagundi Club; the gift-plate of the YMCA; and the Society of Mayflower Descendants.
- Series 6: Indexes and Papers, circa 1930s-1982; 1.0 Linear feet in 3 manuscript boxes
  The indexes are filed in original order by subject, and arranged according to either a primary (Box 46) or supplementary (Box 47) relationship to each series in the collection. The correspondence and papers in Box 48 are loosely organized by date, and the bookplates filed according to original order.
  The primary indexes in Box 46 generally correspond to the arrangement of bookplates and act as useful guides to finding individual plates in the collection. However, these indexes are sometimes inconsistent with the physical collection at the item level. For instance, the "Illustrated" index lists both the owner and the engraver, and though the particular plate is indexed under "Illustrated," it will be filed in the collection under the series "Engravers of Bookplates." Lionel W. Rothschild is indexed under "Illustrated," yet his bookplate is boxed under Sherborn (in which index Rothschild is not listed). The same is found for several other "Illustrated" plates, which are boxed under the engraver. Conversely, Mrs. Theodore Roosevelt is indexed in "Illustrated" and though engraved by Sidney L. Smith, Mrs. Roosevelt is also boxed in "Illustrated." Such cross-indexing recurs in the collection, and requires the researcher to check multiple indexes and boxes before finding the physical location of a particular plate.
  The J.W. Spenceley index is marked at the top in pencil, "not in Miss Toedteberg's list," which description may also apply to the indexes for all engravers' collections. The French index is pencil marked to note that Emma's bookplate has been added to the collection. The Sidney L. Smith index has been previously amended in pencil where the listings are out of alphabetical order. However, the bookplates in the boxes are alphabetized according to the pre-amended indexing order, which might suggest that the author of the original index also boxed the collection. Unlike the French collection, which indicates a post-Emma stage of processing, here the Smith box follows the original index.
  Finally, many of the indexes show traces of having been updated. For example, some are marked in pencil to indicate mistakes in alphabetization, and some show typewritten amendations to the lists. A reference to the "unmarked green box" remains a mystery.
  Box 48 contains bookplates and correspondence acquired by Harriet Stryker-Rodda, Long Island Historical Society librarian in the 1960s. Numerous unmounted and uncollected bookplates are included, as well as a one-page outline of the materials and a detailed index of the bookplates.